בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is קמ"ג, kuf mem gimmel,
143. We pick up at the bottom of ק"מ ב' עמוד ב',
kuf mem beis amud beis, and we're dealing with these issues about
זכין לעובר zachin le'ubar or not. The גמרא Gemara ended with והלכתא
המזכה לעובר לא קנה. v'hilchasa hamizakeh le'ubar lo kanah. That was where
we ended, that you cannot transfer property to a fetus. The question
is, two implicitly addressed questions of the conclusion were: what if can
a fetus inherit? The basic thrust of the סוגיא sugya was yes;
תוספות Tosafos and the רשב"ם Rashbam say yes, even as a עובר
ubar he inherits. And what if you try to transfer to an
עובר, ubar, to a fetus, not now that he's a fetus, but
it should take effect when he is born? That was a debate
of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and תוספות, Tosafos, somebody, רב הונא Rav
Huna and רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, and that was not clearly resolved
either. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. ההוא דאמר לדביתהו, Hahu d'amar lidvasaihu,
it starts with the word דאמר, de'amar,
yeah, that it's your son.
Oh, thank you. And the גמרא Gemara said the way to explain
the משנה mishnah about the person who's trying to gift money to
his unborn child is that when it's a person's own child, they
are able to transfer, which makes it sound like it's much more
of a דעת da'as concern than it is a what do you
call it? Than it is a technical problem, like that the עובר
ubar is seen as not existing at all. Okay, so again, what?
Yes, I think that's correct. Yes, that's going, that's flat. Okay, so
we take up on ק"מ ב' עמוד ב' kuf mem beis amud
beis and we've concluded והלכתא המזכה לעובר לא קנה; v'hilchasa hamizakeh le'ubar
lo kanah; you can't actively transfer to an עובר. ubar. As was
said, there's an exception if it's your child. There's a question if
it happens automatically by ירושה, yerushah, and now we continue. ההוא דאמר
לדביתהו, Hahu d'amar lidvasaihu, it starts with the word דאמר, de'amar, about
a third of the way from the bottom. Okay, somebody said to
his wife, נכסי לבני דהוו לי מינך: nechasai livni dehavu li minach:
all of my property should be to my children that will be
born from you. Meaning he was already had a first marriage, he
has some kids from the first marriage, now he's getting married to
his second wife, and he makes and he basically does on a
קנין kinyan or מתנת שכיב מרע mattnas sh'chiv mei'ra or whatever he
does, he's trying to transfer all of his property to the future,
hopefully not מתנת שכיב מרע, mattnas sh'chiv mei'ra, he has to have
a chance to have the kids. He doesn't have the kids yet,
okay, but anyway, so through an act of קנין, kinyan, transferring all
of my property to the kids that I will have from you.
Now the problem is that those kids don't exist yet; not only
do they not exist yet, she's not even pregnant. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אתא ברא קשישא, Asa bra keshisha,
so the older son came from the first wife. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, and he said to his father, ההוא גברא מאי תהוי עליה?
hahu gavra mai tavei alei? And this person, what's going to be
about him? Meaning, hey, what about me? You're giving away all my
property to my future half-brothers? I mean, what, you're disinheriting me? אמר
ליה, Amar lei,
so the father said back to the son from the first wife,
זיל קני כחד מברא, Zil kani kechad mibra, fine, go do a
קנין kinyan and you should get a portion equal to the portion
that I'm giving my future kids from this wife. Okay, so what
does he do? Literally? He gives him a handkerchief or something. By
קנין kinyan right now. Yeah, the son gives the father a handkerchief
and he says and I'm transferring to you now an equal portion
of the estate according to the number, you know, equal to whatever
one of the other kids from the second wife will get.
Were there witnesses here? Witnesses that have to write it?
Well, there needs witnesses to prove it, but doesn't need witnesses for
it to be binding. An act of קנין kinyan is binding even
without witnesses.
Or it could be a סודר sudar right, now נכסי? nechasai?
Yeah,
but it's not we don't know exactly what that property is and
it's not determined yet, but in theory, yes. Oh, thank you. Because
that would be more concrete which specific piece of property. But if
the person dies and he's left with, you know, four hundred dollars
and three kids from his second wife, then those three kids and
this kid, they'll each get a hundred dollars. Okay, so that's what
he did. He transferred to him an equal stake in the estate
with those other kids.
So now, you know this guy was the בכור? bechor?
Yeah, well, he was not doing it through death, he was doing
it through a
קנין, kinyan, okay? You can't transfer the חלק בכורה, cheilek bechorah, but
you can rid yourself of all your property, divest yourself of all
your property and leave your son with nothing. Okay, so
anyway, thank
you.
הנך ודאי לא קנו, Hanach vadai lo kanu, so
the wives of the future, the children of the future kids of
the new wife definitely were not קונה koneh because they don't exist
yet, okay? And not only I mean we said המזכה לעובר לא
קנה, hamizakeh le'ubar lo kanah, and the רשב"ם Rashbam said that before
he's an עובר, ubar, everybody would agree he's not קונה. koneh. So
the future kids certainly don't get. Okay, now but here's the question.
They don't exist yet. האי אישתכח ליה במקום בניה או לא אישתכח
ליה במקום בניה? Hai ishtachach lei bemakom b'neya o la ishtachach lei
bemakom b'neya?
This kid, this one, is there a portion לטליא? l'talya? טליא Talya
is a word like of a טלא, tla, you know, a kid.
What's the word kid? A kid goat, right? So טליא, talya, you
know, so it's a word of like a young person. I mean
he's the oldest son but whatever. Anyway, it's a kid. This kid,
okay, does he get another portion together with of an additional portion
over his other brothers or not? So if there was, right, here's
the father, right,
here's his wife, wife number one, okay, he had I don't know,
three kids,
alright, she died, he's marrying wife number two and he makes her
this promise, okay? So, the promise to these future kids that don't
yet exist, okay? Okay, so those future kids don't get anything. But
what did he say? He said I'm going to give you,
fine, this kid complained, he said I'm going to give you a
portion equal to those other kids. Okay, now he dies. If he
hadn't said anything, they would have all divided, you know, equally, we'll
ignore the בכור bechor issue for now, okay?
Now though, if again in my scenario where he left behind, where
he left behind $400, do we say well look, had he done
what he wanted to do, they each would have had $100 and
he would have had $100, right? So even though they got nothing
in that act where he did a קנין kinyan with this one
and said take have a portion to equal to that of the
other kids, these other sons, was is that part still good? And
does he still get $100 off the top before you then divide
the rest? And then you divide the remaining $300 amongst these three?
No, amongst these...
there was $400, okay, had what he said happened, each of these
would have got $100 and he would have got $100. This didn't
happen because it couldn't happen. Does he still get the $100 and
then the remaining $300 get inherited by the three kids?
Yeah, but don't the three kids get something at some point?
Like in other words, he
dies.
He dies with $400 to his name.
So you're thinking he'll never get anything?
No, they each get $100.
But those other three?
Yeah, oh, oh, you mean that's true, they also get because they're
just heirs, סתם stam heirs. Right. Okay, that's true. Okay, so
we'd have to divide it up amongst all of them.
Alright, fine, good point Michael. Alright, anyway, is that what we say?
Okay. Alright. Alright, so does he still get the $100 or do
we say since this part of it didn't work, the gifting of
the $100 to him also doesn't work?
In other a thousand question, in other words, first the question was
can you transfer ירושה yerusha through an עובר ubar that hasn't been
born yet?
Well, property, let's not say ירושה. yerusha.
Right, so that's double.
Right, so that's what we said, they certainly don't get. הגמרא Ha-gemara
says that's not even a conversation.
Is he distinct enough in order to give the guy...
well, that's the question. Well, if the first part of the statement
is completely meaningless, does the second part still effective? That's the question
of הגמרא. ha-gemara. Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so it
says like this.
Okay, so
האי חולקא דטליא במקום בניה או לאי חולקא דטליא במקום בניה? hai
chulka d'talya bemakom bneya o lai chulka d'talya bemakom bneya? רבי אבין
ורבי מיישא ורבי
ירמיה דאמרי האי חולקא דטליא במקום בניה.
Rabbi Abin ve-Rabbi Meisha
ve-Rabbi Yirmiyah de-amrei hai chulka d'talya bemakom bneya.
So those three rabbis said he does get, that קנין kinyan is
still binding and he still gets that $100 and the rest get
equally inherited. רבי אבהו ורבי חנינא בר פפי ורבי יצחק נפחא דאמרי
לאי חולקא דטליא במקום בניה. Rabbi Abbahu ve-Rabbi Chanina bar Pappi ve-Rabbi
Yitzchak Nappacha de-amrei lai chulka d'talya bemakom bneya.
He doesn't get. אמר ליה רבי אבהו, Amar lei Rabbi Abbahu, so
it's a nice big debate, three against three. אמר ליה רבי אבהו
לרבי ירמיה, Amar lei Rabbi Abbahu le-Rabbi Yirmiyah, so Rabbi Abbahu who
says he does not have said to Rabbi Yirmiyah who says he
does have,
three kids versus three
kids, now maybe, okay, הלכתא כוותנו הלכתא כוותייכו? Hilcheta kevatanu hilcheta kevataichu?
It's very funny to ask that to the person you're arguing with.
Okay, is the ruling like us or the ruling like you? It's
all very nicely debated. What do you think the bottom line פסק
psak should be? So what do you think he'd say? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so he said to him, פשיטא דהלכתא כוותנו. Pshita de-hilcheta
kevatanu. It's obvious that the ruling is like us. Why? דקשישנא מינייכו.
De-kashishna minaichu. We're older than you. Okay, ולאו הלכתא כוותייכו דדרדקי אתון.
Velav hilcheta kevataichu de-dardakei atun. Not like you, you dirty kids, you're
young. Now, of course, this echoes what we said before. First of
all, הגמרא ha-gemara started by responding to this by saying פשיטא, pshita,
right, that they don't, that these kids don't have. It also used
the phrase ברה קשישא, bera kashisha, the older son, right? So there's
the older kids and the younger. younger kids. I maybe subconsciously did
three and three. So he said, "Of course the הלכה halacha is
like us," you know, "and this פתא pita they don't get because
they're not born yet. פתא pita the לאו lav is not like
you, it's like us, we're קשישא מינייכו, kashisha minaichu, we're older than
you. Okay, דרדקי dardeki
and you're just babies actually, that word דרדקי dardeki is babies. אמר
ליה Amar lei so he said back to him, "מידי בקשישותא תליא
מילתא? Midi bekashishuta talya milta?
What? Is it all about age? בטעמא תליא מילתא, Beta'ama talya milta,
it's about who has the more compelling reason?" Okay, which is a
nice phrase that sometimes is used in some פוסקים poskim right when
they sort of are arguing on greater authorities or whatever. לאו בקשישותא
תליא מילתא, Lav bekashishuta talya milta, it's not just the older authorities
are necessarily the ones that are going to dictate. Okay, it's not
about how old you are, it's who has the compelling reason. וטעמא
מאי? Veta'ama mai? So it's like, "Okay, so what is the what's
your reason? Why do you think your reason that it doesn't work
is so compelling?" So he says, "זיל לגבי רבי אבין, Zil legabei
Rabbi Avin, go to Rabbi Avin דאפרשה ניהליה de'afreshah nihaleih
I explained this to Rabbi Avin וקרקש ביה רישיה vekarkash beih reisheih
בי
מדרשא bei midrasha
and he sort of and he you know and when I explained
it to him he like nodded to me, he you know nodded
shook his you know nodded his head in the בית מדרש." beis
medrash. So again the irony here is I'm explaining it to a
greater authority, Rabbi Avin, if you want to go to Rabbi Avin,
Rabbi Avin is clearly senior, he's a greater authority and I, the
young kid, explained it to this greater authority and he conceded to
my point, right?
Wait, Rabbi Avin was part of these three.
That's true, I guess. Okay, רבי אבין ורבי יצחק ורבי ירמיה דאמיהו.
Rabbi Avin veRabbi Yitzchak veRabbi Yirmiyah de'amihu. Oh no no no, Rabbi
Avin was part of the three that said meaning wait a second
I missed that point. Right. Thank you. So you, your Rabbi Avin
of your opposing right right thank you Michael. So the one who
says that he the kids do not and he's saying, "Look, we're
younger than you but it's about who has the more compelling reason,"
and he said, "And I explained it to Rabbi Avin who's part
of your camp, who's older and he's part of your camp and
he even conceded to me." Okay. So modeling that ultimately the reason
wins out over age and I even explained it to Rabbi Avin,
I missed that point Michael thank you, that is a member of
your own camp, your own opposing camp and he in the end
conceded to me.
Okay. So רבי ירמיה ורבי אבין Rabbi Yirmiyah veRabbi Avin are in
the same camp.
Right, that's the point. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah say they're part of
the older people the older group who say that the son does
not have a portion. Right? No. Yes
they say the son does not have a portion. Oh excuse me
they're part of the older group who say the son does have
a portion. Now I'm getting confused. He's part of the older group
that says the son does have a portion and they're saying, "Oh,
it should go like us because we're older." And he's saying, "No,
it goes by who has a more compelling reason right? We have
the more compelling reason and even Rabbi Avin who's part of you
the older group who says that the son does have a portion
in the end conceded to me." Okay. So אזל
לגביה. Azal legabeih. So he who was it now who said
this? רבי אבהו? Rabbi Abbahu? ורבי ירמיה veRabbi Yirmiyah so went to
Rabbi Avin. So Rabbi Yirmiyah went to Rabbi Avin and אזל לגביה
azal legabeih אמר ליה אלו אמר ליה. amar lei ilu amar lei.
So Rabbi Avin now said, "Yeah you're right and in the end
I switched sides." Why did I switch sides to say that the
son doesn't have a portion? "אילו אמר ליה קני כחמור מי קני?
Ilu amar lei kni kachamor mi kani? Let's say I said to
Michael here, 'Michael take possession of my car just like a donkey
would.' Okay. And Michael we do a קנין. kinyan. Does he own
the car? No because a donkey can't do a קנין. kinyan. So
he didn't say I'm giving you a hundred I'm giving them each
a hundred dollars and you a hundred dollars. If so he would
take possession. What he said was you can take an equal portion
as they get. Well what do they get? Zero. So therefore you
get zero." Okay. So he says this so therefore obviously it's not
going to work. Okay it's not because he said them all in
one sentence. It's because the way what he gave them was framed
as equivalent to what they're getting. Okay. "אילו אמר ליה קני כחמור
מי קני? Ilu amar lei kni kachamor mi kani? דאמר קני כחמור.
De'amar kni kachamor. If somebody says, 'Take possession like a donkey would.'
לא קנה, Lo kanah, it doesn't work. את וחמור. At vechamor. Now
let's say somebody says, 'I want to transfer my car to you
and to your donkey.' Okay. I mean there are people who leave
all their estate to their cats or their dogs. Okay. So רב
נחמן אמר קנה מחצה. Rav Nachman amar kanah mechtza. All right so
he basically said half to you and half to your donkey so
the donkey part didn't work the half to you did work. I
didn't say you should be קונה koneh like your donkey then you
would get nothing. So I'm doing it to you and your donkey
the donkey part doesn't work but the half to you does work.
רב המנונא אמר לא אמר כלום. Rav Hamnuna amar lo amar klum.
No since he basically meant that as a unit like you know
not each of you get half of my car. The two of
you together get my car. So since the donkey can't get the
car you can't get it either the whole thing doesn't work it's
working as a unit and since part of that unit doesn't work
the whole thing falls apart. לא קנה כלום Lo kanah klum and
רב ששת אמר קנה הכל. Rav Sheshes amar kanah hakol. You get
my whole car because since I know that the donkey isn't going
to get right or if maybe another you know then obviously I
meant to give it to you all. That's the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it makes it psychological. I can say it a little
bit different I can say if I'm giving it to you..." to
you if like a corporate entity, it's the flip side of saying
you get nothing, right, even though the side that you get half
is I meant half to the donkey and half to you, so
you get your half. If you say it's one unit, and I'm
giving it to you as a unit, so you could say since
it doesn't work for part of the unit, nothing happens, or you
could say no, it's still owned by the two you know, so
if you think about it as a corporation, right, so you're the
last remaining shareholder of the corporation, you know, the donkey can't, you
know, but still so so but the fact that you're still part
of that unit is enough for you to be קונה koneh the
whole thing. All right, so that's I think the flip side, not
just like oh obviously I didn't really mean and I meant to
give you everything. I meant to give it to you and the
donkey as a unit, but just cause the donkey goes away, you're
still standing, you're still part of that corporate entity, and therefore you're
קונה koneh the whole thing.
This reminds me when back in the days where you know,
pre financial crisis, sending out credit cards to everyone, my uncle got
a credit card in the mail made out to, you know, it
happened to be the dog.
Right. There you go. Okay. All right. So a very good. Okay,
so רב ששת Rav Sheshet by the way notice, I don't know
if people have been noticing that רב ששת Rav Sheshet keeps on
coming up, I mean there's a lot, רב ששת Rav Sheshet keeps
on coming up and says, oh the עובר uber is קונה, koneh,
you're קנה הכל, kana hakol, like he's much more ready to see
that these transactions work. Okay, רב ששת אמר קנה הכל. Rav Sheshet
amar kana hakol. אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshet and also the
language does, מנא אמינא לה, mena amina la, that's like we had
yesterday, how do I know an עובר uber is קונה? koneh? How
do I know that if you're the last one left standing, I
mean or you're the only one, whatever, human being of this group,
you're קונה koneh
everything? דתניא detanya we saw in a ברייתא braita רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosei, רבי יוסי אומר, אין לך מר בקישות אלא פנימי שבו. Rabbi
Yosei omer ein lacha mar bekishut ela penimi shebo, So you've got
קישות kishut which is some type of I don't know what is
it, a gourd or something? A zucchini. A zucchini. Okay, so apparently
the inside is bitter, I don't know, that's not true for the
zucchinis I eat, but anyway. קישוא שוטה. kishu shoteh. Oh okay, whatever.
Anyway, we have a certain type,
some type of a gourd of something, some sort, the inside is
very bitter. Now I'm going to explain this like תוספות, Tosafot, the
רשב"ם Rashbam explains it a little bit differently, but anyway the point
is I tried to be מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah on my bushels
of these gourds. Okay, and I was מפריש mafrish one, and this
is the way תוספות Tosafot explains it, if everybody who have the
English is going to tell me that they translate differently, they're going
by the רשב"ם Rashbam I'm assuming, but that's anyway this is how
תוספות Tosafot explains it, which is so I tried to be מפריש
תרומה mafrish terumah on all of these gourds, I took two percent,
which I normally do, let's say I just took one gourd, there
were fifty gourds, so one gourd is two percent. Okay, and then
good, it's תרומה. terumah. Then I open it up and it's sour,
it's all turned bitter and sour and spoiled. So there's a חכמים
Chachamim that say, okay, you gotta take תרומה terumah again. All right,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says, or actually they say both are תרומה,
terumah, this is תרומה terumah and take תרומה terumah again. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei says look, the inside is the most bitter sour part.
The side near the top, near the edge is still edible. So
all you have to do is he said add a little bit
of another gourd and make up the difference. Okay, so that's what
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says.
Sorry, if all gourds are bitter inside and then why is this
any different?
Yeah, so that's why the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it. He doesn't read
it that all gourds, he reads it like or maybe that gourd
in general are more bitter in the inside, so therefore this one,
the only part that's really inedible, so normally they're all edible, but
this one went inedible, it's only the inner part that really turned
inedible, the outer part is still edible. That's why תוספות Tosafot reads
it. Okay, based on the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Okay, רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi
Yosei omer, אין לך מר בקישות אלא פנימי שבו, ein lacha mar
bekishut ela penimi shebo. the only part that's really going to be
bitter and inedible is the inner part, ופנכא כשיהא תורם upancha kesheyeha
torem therefore if you have to now deal with the fact that
it turned sour, מוסיף על החיצון שבו ותורם, mosif al hachitzon shebo
vetorem, add, make up the difference of the inner part, but the
rest is still good. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר amar the גמרא Gemara says ותורם, vetorem, אמאי את וחמור
הוא? amai at vechamor hu? It's you and a donkey. You know,
that would have been the first thing I would have thought of
when I read that משנה mishna to see how relevant that is
to this case. So the relevance is you really have to be
creative to think this way, but the relevance is, here's my gourd,
okay, here's the inner part that's sour, here's the outer part that's
still good. When I took it, there were fifty gourds here, okay.
Now at the end of the day though, okay,
you know, what I when I was taking it what I was
thinking was I'm taking all of this on all of those, right?
So in the end though, which part really is the only part
that was legitimate תרומה? terumah? The outer part. The inner part was
spoiled and not fit to be eaten. So this was את וחמור.
at vechamor. Okay, I wanted this and this and I said as
a unit I want this to be תרומה. terumah. Now the תרומה
terumah didn't work on the inner part, it was inedible.
It's not necessarily that it didn't work on the inner part, but
meaning you're supposed to give a fiftieth, so it's not like...
well that's another point which is you're saying which the גמרא Gemara
could answer. Michael knows that the הלכה halacha is that even if
you give even a tiny amount for תרומה terumah it works. So
you could but
nevertheless though the point is that I wanted these to work as
a unit in my mind. In my mind, it was all that
they should work. So the point is, well if part of it
isn't working, the whole thing shouldn't work. Because I didn't think I
want this to work as one type of תרומה terumah and that
to work, right? I wanted them all to work equally. Okay, so
anyway that's the comparison of the גמרא. Gemara. Let's see the inside.
Are you supposed to be opening this thing up? I mean, like
what do you...
Oh, maybe it's when you give it to a כהן, kohen, maybe
it starts smelling. I don't know. It's a good question. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: שאני התם דמדאורייתא תרומה מעלייתא היא.
Shani hatam demide'oraisa terumah ma'alyasa hi. Even the inner part is good
תרומה. terumah. Why? דאמר רבי אילעא מנין לתורם מן הרע על היפה
שתרומתו תרומה. De'amar Rabbi Ila minayin latoram min hara al hayafa sheterumaso
terumah. How do you know that when you take the bad on
the good that it still works? שנאמר ולא תשאו עליו חטא בהרימכם
את חלבו ממנו. Shene'emar velo sisu alav cheit beharimchem es chelbo mimenu.
You should not have a sin when you take the fat from
it. If you take the good from your crop for the תרומה,
terumah, you won't sin. So meaning, but if you take the bad,
you will sin. So ואם אינו קדוש, ve'im eino kadosh, now if
it didn't work, if trying to take the bad on the good
was ineffective, so ואם
אינו קדוש נשיאת חטא למה, ve'im eino kadosh nesi'as cheit lamah, why
would you bear the burden of your sin? So if you're going
to sin by taking the bad, it must mean that it's effective.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: מכאן לתורם מן הרע על היפה
שתרומתו תרומה. mikan latoram min hara al hayafa sheterumaso terumah. It works.
Now of course there's a difference between being bad and being inedible,
right? But it seems that the way the גמרא Gemara is answering
it is saying that in theory this really works because in this
case this really is תרומה. terumah. Maybe we demand that you add
to it so that it's all good תרומה, terumah, but in principle
even the stuff on the inside is still considered רע, ra, bad,
but still תרומה, terumah, still good enough to be תרומה. terumah. Which
again, is not necessarily, you know, is a change maybe in how
we were assuming the facts.
But the חלב cheilev here is the good.
If you take the good, the fat, then you won't sin. If
you take the bad, you will sin. Right, I know, it means
do it the right way and you won't get into trouble. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, אמר רב מרדכי
בר אבשי מותיב רב אביא תיובתא. Amar Rav Mordechai bar Avashi masiv
Rav Avya tiyuvta. So
we still don't know what this הלכה halacha is about את וחמור.
at vachamor. So רב אביא Rav Avya asks a challenge to this
question about to the claim that את וחמור at vachamor
could work, you know, partially or fully or whatever. Or what? The
three of each other, the three brothers-in-law?
Or no, but
actually
the question was, no, the question is on the claim that it
doesn't work, that nobody is קונה. koneh. Okay, here is the challenge
to the claim that it doesn't work for anything, for anyone. מעשה
בחמש נשים. Ma'aseh bechamesh nashim. This is a משנה. Mishna. A story
of five women, ובהן שתי אחיות, uvehen shtei achayos, a group of
five women, two sisters. וליקט אחד כלכלה של תאנים. Veliket echad kalkalah
shel te'einim. And somebody came into their, these five women had a
women's cooperative and they had a, they had an orchard of fig
trees and somebody walked into the orchard and picked a basket filled
with figs, ושלהן הייתה, veshelahen haysah, and it really belonged to these
five women. Okay, and then, ושביעית הייתה. veshevi'is haysah. By the way,
it's also
שמיטה. shemittah. ואמר, Ve'amar, and then he took this basket of שמיטה
shemittah figs that belonged to these women and said to this group
of women: הרי כולכם מקודשות לי בכלכלה זו. Harei kulchem mekudashos li
bekalkalah zo. I am marrying all five of you with this basket
of figs that I just picked off of your fig tree. Okay,
and
the problem is two sisters. וקיבלה אחת מהן על ידי כולן. Vekiblah
achas mehen al yedei kulan. And one of them accepted them on
behalf of all, so presumably they said, fine, sounds like a good
deal to us. אמרו חכמים, Ameru chachamim, so the sages said, אין
האחיות מקודשות. Ein ha'achayos mekudashos. The sisters aren't married, but he is
married to the other three. Now, first of all, why is he
married?
Why can't he be married to one of the sisters?
Okay, I will answer that question. But why first of all is
he married? Part of the חידוש chiddush here is, is that the
way the גמרא Gemara explains this is, the fact that it's שמיטה,
shemittah, you could say makes it worse. Maybe שמיטה shemittah has
קדושת שביעית, kedushas shevi'is, לאכילה ולא לאיבוד, le'ochla velo le'ibud, you can't
use it in other ways, maybe that would limit it from being
considered money that could do קידושין. kiddushin. But the גמרא Gemara says
no, you could take fruit of קדושת שביעית kedushas shevi'is and be
מקדש mekadesh with it. So that's one of the things we learn
from this, that it works for money of קידושין. kiddushin. The other
thing we learn though is that גזל gezel would not work for
קידושין. kiddushin. If he took it from their trees and it wasn't
שמיטה, shemittah, then he would be stealing it. The only reason he
wasn't stealing it when he took it from their trees was because
it was שמיטה shemittah and it's not theirs either. What? It wasn't
really theirs, it didn't really belong to them because of the שמיטה.
shemittah. So therefore, one thing we learn from this is that גזל
gezel does not work for קידושין, kiddushin, שמיטה shemittah produce does work
for קידושין. kiddushin. And now the third thing we learn which is
there, why don't we say one of the sisters is מקודשת, mekudeshes,
we just don't know which one? Okay, so because, so true, halachically
you can't be married, not only is it an עבירה, aveirah, you
can't be married to two sisters, it doesn't take effect because it's
an איסור כרת. issur kares. But why don't we say it's one
and you don't know which one? So the third thing we learn
from this is,
is קידושין שאינה מסורה לביאה kiddushin she'einah mesurah levi'ah is not קידושין.
kiddushin. A קידושין kiddushin that would never allow for it to be
consummated, not just physically like there's a medical problem or something like
that, halachically could never be consummated is not, is not קידושין. kiddushin.
Why halachically could this never be consummated with either sister? Because if
he would have intercourse with one sister, it might be the one
that he isn't married to and then he would be עובר over
on the איסור דאורייתא issur de'oraisa of his wife's sister. So therefore,
since for each sister there's no way it could be consummated if
you don't know which one, it doesn't work for either.
I thought it was actually an application of את וחמור. at vachamor.
We're getting to את וחמור. at vachamor.
No, but that's in terms of the other wives. Since this one
act, since this one act did not act for these two sisters
based on a different principle, right, but let it work—I understand, I
understand—but let it also not work for the other three. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אחיות לא מקודשות, achayos lo mekudashos, it's the sisters aren't married.
הנכריות מקודשות, ha'nochriyos mekudashos, the unrelated women are—that's what it means, not
non-Jewish or whatever, unrelated women are married. ואמאי? v'amai? אתה וחמור היא.
ata v'chamur hi. If he tried to do all five at once,
right, so okay, but not between the two sisters. That's a different
logic. Okay.
Oh my gosh. Okay, right. Alright, moving on. It's true though. I
mean, look, it's willing to call תרומה terumah whatever, it's okay. It
calls unborn sons אתה וחמור. ata v'chamur. I don't think you can
say this is sexist here. But anyway, אתה וחמור היא. ata v'chamur
hi. אמר ליה, amar lei, okay, so ah, so you see that
proves that אתה וחמור ata v'chamur doesn't work. Okay, I mean excuse
me, does work. At least, you know, at least it works for
those for whom it can work. Whether you get half or whether
you get whole, maybe we could debate that in the case where
you tried to give your entire car to you and a חמור.
chamur. But at least for—at least it works partially, minimally, because the
other three women are married.
Okay, I'm moving on. Okay, אמר ליה היינו דחזאי רב הונא בר
אויה בחלמא. amar lei hainu d'chazai Rav Huna bar Avia b'chalma. That
is, ah, thank you, you know, you told me that רב אויה
Rav Avia asked this question. So now I understand why last night
I saw רב אויה Rav Avia in my dream. Because why did
I see him in my dream? דחזאי רב אויה תיובתא? d'chazai Rav
Avia tiyufta? Because now I realize that he had a question to
ask on my position. So now it all makes sense why I
saw him in my dream. Okay, that's good. But what's the answer
to the question? So it says, here's the answer. לאו מי אוקימנא
דאמר הראויות מכם לביאה יתקדשו לי? lav mi oukimna d'amar hareuyos mikem
l'via yiskadeshu li? No, because the גמרא Gemara there in קידושין Kiddushin
says there's—what about the position that says that קידושין שאינן מסורין לביאה
kiddushin she'einan mesuran l'via is good קידושין? kiddushin? So how does he
explain this משנה? Mishna? Why isn't it that one of the sisters
is married and we just don't know which one? So he—so this
position, I think it's שמואל Shmuel says, no, the משנה Mishna is
missing an important detail. He doesn't just say I'm marrying all five
of you. He says, I'm marrying all, you know, all five of
you—what's the line?—that I'm able to have, that it would be permissible
for me to have intercourse with. So, you know, any and all
of the five of you. So he explicitly says it's going to
work for those for whom it will—it can be effective for. So
once he qualifies that, therefore שמואל Shmuel says, you know, that's why
it doesn't work for either sister. Normally, if he just said to
two sisters I'm marrying one of you, whatever, and tried to do
them both at once, it wouldn't work—it would work, שמואל Shmuel would
say it would work for one, we just don't know which one.
Here the reason it doesn't work for either is because he explicitly
says I'm only doing this act for those—for those women here for
whom it would be possible to have intercourse. Okay, so therefore he's
explicitly excluding the two sisters. That's how שמואל Shmuel defends his position,
that that's why the two sisters are excluded. Otherwise one would be
married, we just wouldn't know which one. But once you say that's
what he said, it also solves the אתה וחמור ata v'chamur problem,
because he's not saying I'm doing it to all five of you
as one indivisible unit. He's saying I'm doing it to whichever of
you it is possible that it can work. So once he qualified
it that way, he's dividing it. Right? If I say I'm giving
it to you and the donkey, whichever one of you is able
to do the קניין, kinyan, nobody would debate that you would be
קונה. koneh. Right? So that's how we're sort of qualifying it. But
certainly on the surface, it's a pretty good proof that it works
for the remainder. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like
this. ההוא
דאמר
לה לדביתהו. hahu d'amar la l'devishu. Another case. A man said to
his wife, נכסיי ליכי ולבניי. nichasai lichi u'l'vnaich.
I'm going to give all my property to you and to my
kids. Okay?
And he does this as a שכיב מרע, shchiv meyra, you know,
as some type of a מתנה. matana. Okay. אמר רב יוסף, amar
Rav Yosef, so here's an interesting question. How much does she get?
Equal to any individual kid or fifty percent?
Or you like—right, exactly. You and my kids.
Right. Well, it's not the same question as before. קנתה פלגא. kansa
palga. She gets half. He say you and my kids, you get
half and my kids get half. Okay. It may be said you
together with my kids, you know, or something like that, maybe that
would imply like as equal to any one of them. But you
and my kids means you get half and they get half. אמר
רב יוסף מנא אמינא לה, amar Rav Yosef mina amina la, so
the same way רב ששת Rav Sheshet was saying מנא אמינא לה.
mina amina la. מנא אמינא לה *mina amina lah*, now רב יוסף
Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* saying מנא אמינא לה *mina amina lah*. דתניא
דתנא ברייתא *detanya detanna braitah*, רבי אומר *Rabbi omer*, והיתה לאהרן ולבניו
*vehaitah le-aharon u-le-vanav*, you know, so that is by the, by the
לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*. So רבי *Rabbi* says מחצה mechtsa, לאהרן מחצה
לבניו *mechtzah le-aharon mechtzah le-vanav*. He gets half of every, every week
there's twelve loaves of bread, he gets half, he gets six and
all the other כהנים *kohanim* get six. The כהן גדול *kohen gadol*
gets six. Actually, the משנה Mishna *mishnah* there says five, the גמרא
Gemara *gemara* describes how, but anyway in principle it should be six.
Okay, אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*, so you see לאהרן ולבניו
*le-aharon u-le-vanav* means even though the בניו *banav* is a group of
many people, fifty-fifty. אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*, בשלמא התם *bishlama
hatam*, אהרן בר חלוקה הוא *Aharon bar chaluka hu*, you know, if
you hadn't said anything, he anyway would have gotten, he's a כהן
*kohen*. He would have gotten some of the bread. So, so להכי
פרטיה רחמנא למשקל פלגא *lehachi parteih rachmana lemishkal palga*. So you didn't
have to say לאהרן ולבניו *le-aharon u-le-vanav*, he, you know, you would
have said לכהנים *lekohanim*, they all would have gotten. So אהרן ולבניו
*Aharon u-levanav* you're giving him extra weight. And the extra weight is
you're saying he gets half. אשה לאו בת ירושה yerusha, היא *Ishah
lav bat yerushah hi*. If you hadn't said anything about his wife,
she wouldn't have gotten anything. So therefore when he said, "you and
the kids," דייו *dayo*,
it's sufficient that we interpret it to mean שתטול כאחד מן הבנים
*shetitnol ke-echad min ha-banim*, that she should just get equal to one
kid. Now you could say it means like, ah, she doesn't deserve
to get anything, so she should be happy by just getting equal,
right? Sort of like, but I don't think he's saying that way,
or I'd like to think he's not saying that. I think what
he's saying is that since she wouldn't have gotten anything without him
saying anything, we should interpret his statement, you know, as saying equal
to the kids. Like, you know, she's being included in something she
otherwise wouldn't have been included in, as opposed to if you were
already included and singled out, you get half. But if you weren't
included yet, it should just be read as you're being included.
Okay, so if we have, if these kids are around? Yeah. Okay.
Yeah.
So if let's say he had a,
he's on his deathbed let's say. So let's say he had his
wife, two boys and a girl. Does the girl get too?
Well, if he said kids, בנים banim *banim* could mean sons here.
Okay, so we wouldn't include the girl?
Well, we're going to get to that later. But if he says
בנים banim. *banim*, you know, and not, you know, my children or,
then
I was just asking if
he said, if he said kids then we would include the girl.
But I was thinking kids, but probably more accurately should be read
as sons.
From the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* at any given point, the כהן
גדול *kohen gadol* would get six and
everyone else would get like a crumb? Yeah, basically. Okay, although that's
according to רבי *Rabbi*, and anyway the six becomes five for a
different reason. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like this, איני *eini*,
is that really true? That in those scenarios she would only get
equal to one of the sons? Right? Michael's correct, I should have
been saying sons, that's more accurately what we're saying. והא עובדא הוה
בנהרדעא *veha uvda hava bi-Nahardea*, there was a case just like this
in נהרדעא *Nahardea*, ואדביה שמואל פלגא *ve-adbeih Shmuel palga*, and שמואל *Shmuel*
gave her half. והוה עובדא בטבריא *vahava uvda bi-Tverya*, there was a
case like this in טבריא *Tverya*, ואדביה רבי יוחנן פלגא *ve-adbeih Rabbi
Yochanan palga*, and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* collected for her half. So
they actually did פסקן pasken *pasken* like this, that it does mean
half. First of all, it's also fascinating to find out that this
is what people are doing, that the wife doesn't inherit according to
הלכה halacha. *halachah*, and at least some people are giving them an
equal inheritance to the kids. Okay, ותו *v'tu*, and in addition, כי
אתא רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר *ki ata Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef
amar*, ההוא דמי כלילא *hahu dmei kelila* דשדו דבי מלכא אאבולי ואאיסטרוגי
*deshadu devei malka a-avulei ve-a-istrugei*. So there was the cost for paying
for a new crown, and that's כלילא *kelila* is a crown, and
the king's,
you know, house, you know,
basically authority, castle, whatever, whatever, imposed the cost of this crown on
the אבולי *avulei* and איסטרוגי *istrugei*. So אבולי *avulei* are like the
wealthy people and the איסטרוגי *istrugei*, at least the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
says I think it means sort of like... פרוזבול *pruzbul*... exactly. And
איסטרוגי *istrugei*, I think he says means
or like the nobility or the officers. How do they translate this?
Officers. Now, the rich people are like the אבולי *avulei* are the
.1%, the איסטרוגי *istrugei* are the 1-percenters. Okay. So how is that
cost of that crown to be divided? ואמר רבי *ve'amar Rabbi*, so
רבי *Rabbi* said, נסבי אבולי פלגא ואיסטרוגי פלגא *nisbi avulei palga ve-istrugei
palga*. Same idea. He said on A and on B, let them
each pay half. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says so you see
that that's a good basis to say that when you say A
and B, you mean each pays half, each gets half. הכי השתא
hachi hashta? *hachi hashta*? How can you compare this case to that?
Meaning some of those cases obviously where we actually פסקן'ד *paskened* by
the woman and the kids, that clearly shows that, you know, that
according to those rabbis it would mean half and half. But this
case of the crown is not necessarily evidence. Why not? התם מעיקרא
כי הוו כתבי אאבולי הוו כתבי *hatam me-ikara ki havo katvei a-avulei
havo katvei*. Originally, the obligation was only on the, on the super
rich, okay? ואיסטרוגי הוו מסייעי בהדייהו *ve-istrugei havo mesay'ei bahadeihu*, and the
איסטרוגי *istrugei*, the 1-percenters chipped in a little bit. But basically the
real obligation was totally on the super rich. וידע מלכא דהוו מסייעי
*ve-yada malka de-havo mesay'ei*, and the king found out "Oh, you're helping,"
you might as well help more. השתא *hashta*, okay, so השתא מאי
דקא כתבי אאבולי ואיסטרוגי למימר דהאי פלגא ודהאי פלגא *hashta mai de-ka
katvei a-avulei ve-istrugei lemimar de-hai palga ve-de-hai palga*. It's sort of like
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* said before about אהרן ובניו *Aharon u-vanav*. Okay?
Right? You know, the 1-percenters were doing a little bit. So now
that they're being explicitly identified, it means you get 50%—I mean not
that you get, you have to pay. But they were already in
the פרשה *parsha*. So by identifying him, it's giving him that much
weight. But in the case about the wife and the kids, since
she wasn't in the פרשה *parsha*, he's... insisting against these other rabbis
who פסקן fifty-fifty, that in that case the wife would only get
equal to the kids, or equal to the sons.
Yes. At some point in the Hellenistic period, I
mean... the בולי Bulei also had leadership status like the בנים banim
by the way. They weren't just like super rich. I don't know
if that's the reality.
Right. Okay, interesting. All right, so now the משנה Mishna. says like
this. We don't we still don't know. But we're still we're still
working it out. מתיב רבי זירא. Mative Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira asked: האומר הרי עלי מנחה מאה עשרון להביא בשני כלים. Ha'omer
harei alay mincha mei'ah isaron lehavi bishnei keilim. I obligate myself to
bring a מנחה mincha of a hundred עשרוןs, isaron you know, whatever
that unit, and I'm going to bring them in two vessels. והלכה
V'halacha is the following: that you know the famous line of רבי
זירא? Rabbi Zeira? Right. Thank you. ס'איז א שישים?
S'iz
a shishim?
Yeah, exactly. Something so you know, Michael. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
that כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו, kol haraui l'bila ein
bila m'akevet bo, something could could be done, you don't always need
to do it, it's just that it has to have the potential.
That's based on actually this משנה. Mishna The משנה mishnah. says that
you can't bring a מנחה mincha in more than sixty עשרון isaron
in one vessel. Why? Because the מנחה mincha has to be mixed
with the oil. And so the גמרא Gemara says, and more than
sixty the גמרא Gemara says that more than sixty עשרון isaron in
one vessel, you know, if you don't have an industrial size to
you know, machinery, you cannot get a decent way to mix that
together with the with the oil. So the גמרא Gemara. says okay,
but why should that be necessary? I mean we פסקן בדיעבד b'diavad
you don't have to mix it with the oil. And here's and
here's the famous line, I'm not using this line here but I
just wanted to bring it in, he says no: כל הראוי לבילה,
kol haraui l'bila, if it would be possible to mix it, אין
בילה מעכבת בו, ein bila m'akevet bo, if you didn't mix it
it's still כשר. kosher. But more than sixty עשרון isaron in one
vessel is not fit to be mixed. There's no way you could
mix it. So therefore it's no good. Anyway, that's the principle that
if you give a big מנחה, mincha, more than sixty עשרון, isaron,
you have to bring it in two separate vessels. So somebody said,
I will do a מנחה mincha of a hundred עשרון. isaron. He
knew this הלכה. halacha He's been to the דף יומי. Daf Yomi.
So he explicitly said, and I'm going to bring it in two
vessels. So how do you divide the hundred עשרון isaron in the
two vessels? So it says, מביא שישים בכלי אחד וארבעים בכלי אחד,
meivi shishim bikli echad v'arbaim bikli echad, you do sixty and forty.
So why don't we say that anytime you don't specify, you mean
equal division? Now of course you could make distinctions between if I
say to A and to B I mean fifty-fifty. If I say
this this amount in two vessels, maybe I have my discretion how
to divide it. It's different than saying A and B creates an
equivalency, right? A hundred עשרון isaron in two vessels isn't creating an
equivalency. But the גמרא Gemara has another answer anyway. ואם הביא חמישים
בכלי אחד וחמישים בכלי אחד יצא. v'im heivi chamishim bikli echad v'chamishim
bikli echad yatza. And so the end of this is, and if
but if you do fifty-fifty it works בדיעבד. b'diavad. So maybe what
really bothers the גמרא Gemara is that it frames it as a
בדיעבד, b'diavad, like it's not just סתם stam it's at your discretion.
So the גמרא Gemara. says, הביא אין לכתחילה לא, heivi in l'chatchila
lo, only בדיעבד b'diavad you can split it. ואי סלקא דעתך כל
כי האי גוונא, v'i salka dach'tach kol ki hai gavna, since it's
an interesting phrase of the גמרא. Gemara, If you think things like
this, like I think the גמרא Gemara a little bit recognizes it
isn't identical to the other case. The other case you made an
equivalency: you and my kids. But nevertheless, if in that case we
translated it as fifty-fifty, so then in this case even though it's
more general, a hundred and two, you certainly should have the discretion
to do fifty-fifty. That should certainly be acceptable לכתחילה. l'chatchila. ואי אמרת
כל כי האי גוונא פלגא ופלגה הוא, v'i amrat kol ki hai
gavna palga u'palga hu, if you think that similar cases like A
and B means fifty-fifty, so in this case אפילו לכתחילה נמי, afilu
l'chatchila nami, you should at least have the ability to choose to
do it you know fifty and fifty and you shouldn't have to
do sixty and forty לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So why do we demand sixty
and forty? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי השתא? What type of
a comparison is that? התם אנן סהדי דהאי גברא מעיקרא לקורבן גדול
קא מיכוון. hatam anan sahadi de-hai gavra mei-ikara l'korban gadol ka michavein.
There we know the person ideally wanted to bring it all in
one vessel. He wanted one big קורבן korban of a hundred. There
was just a הלכה halacha that prevented him from doing that. והא
דקאמר בשני כלים, ve-ha d'ka-amar bishnei keilim, so why did he divide
it into two קורבנות? korbanot? דידע דלא אפשר לעשותו בכלי אחד d'yada
d'la efshar la-asoto bikli echad because he knew that there was an
upper limit, you couldn't bring more than a certain amount in one
vessel, but ideally he wanted it one unit. So therefore
it's the overage that gets moved to another vessel. Right? Ideally you
didn't want two קורבנות korbanot of fifty, you wanted one of a
hundred. Okay? You couldn't do one of a hundred, so any extra
has to get moved off into the next vessel. Okay, so כמה
דאפשר לאתויי מייתינן, kama d'efshar l'aituyei maitinan, as much as you can
bring in one vessel you bring because that's more in line with
what his intent was. Okay, so we still don't have an answer
to you and my and my and my sons, whether it means
fifty-fifty or you're equal to one of the sons. So now the
הלכתא... hilch'ta... Michael, you should be so happy, so many of these
סוגיות sugyot are ending with הלכתא's. hilch'ta והלכתא, v'hilch'ta, the
הלכה halakhah is כוותיה דרב יוסף kavatei d'Rav Yosef בשדה עניין ומחצה.
bisadeh inyan u'mechtza. Okay, now that's a famous line. We rule like
רב יוסף in שדה, sadeh, that's the discussion over in שבועות, Shevuot,
which was I forget what the case was, but anyway it was
some dispute about a field. Okay. עניין inyan was, if you might
remember, there's a question about when you do a קניין, kinyan, when
you do a קניין סודר, kinyan sudar, you have a certain a
few seconds to retract. Okay? You might remember that.
So as long as
they're עסוקין באותו עניין... asukin b'oto inyan... And here מחצה, Rav Yosef's
ruling that if you say "you and my sons," it's half and
half. We treat it as an equivalency. Okay,
another case.
ההוא דשדר פיסקא דשיריאי לביתיה. Hahu d'shadar piska d'shira'i l'veiteh. This is
going to be very similar to the previous one. Somebody sent like
a package full of cloth or actually שיריאי shira'i refers to silk
or whatever, what is it, linen? I keep on forgetting which is
which. שיריאי, shira'i, oh silk. Silk, right. Anyway, so he said like
all of these silk swatches, not swatches, whatever,
bolts of silk or whatever, to his house. אמר רב אמי, Amar
Rav Ami, so now and he said, "This is for, you know,
here, this is a gift for the house." Okay, so who gets
what? Okay, so אמר רב אמי, Amar Rav Ami, so Rav Ami
said, הראוים לבנים לבנים הראוים לבנות לבנות. hara'uyim l'vanim l'vanim hara'uyim l'vanos
l'vanos. The stuff that can be, you know, the type of the
silk that can be used for the kids, for the sons is
used for them, the ones for the girls is the girls.
He says wasn't he supposed to
give it to his wife or something? Yeah, I don't know why
we assume that. Anyway, so and I also don't know what you
do if it's not clear. If like if it's raw material, because
פיסקא דשיריאי, piska d'shira'i, the, you know, the רשב"ם Rashbam says, ראוים
לבנים מלבושי זכר, re'uyim l'vanim malvushei zachar, which is all very nice
if it's actual clothing. But if it's bolts of the material, which
is what פיסקא piska sounds more like, then how do you determine
what type of material? I guess what, if it's blue, if it's
pink? I mean, I don't know how you're supposed to know. It's
not very helpful if you don't know, you know, if it's indeterminate.
But anyway, ולא אמרן אלא דלית ליה כלתא, v'lo amran ela d'leis
lei kalla, but the basic point is that we interpret it that
he's sending it to his kids. Okay? But that we only say
if he doesn't have a daughter-in-law. אבל אית ליה כלתא, Aval is
lei kalla, if he has a daughter-in-law, לכלתיה שדר. l'kallateih shadar. Then
he's sending it to his daughter-in-law. I don't know why, like maybe
if he just got married you could understand it. Why do we
assume that if he's got a daughter-in-law of twenty years? I mean,
maybe, again, I don't know, maybe because she's the outsider so he
wants to make her feel at home so he was going to
interpret this act of, you know,
more that he's going to want to welcome her in.
But I still might imagine if the other daughters are
married. ובנתיה לא נסיבן. u'vnoseih lo nesivan.
That's right. He says that if he has, thank you, he says
if he has unmarried daughters, then he would have a prior obligation
to them. I guess putting them in nice clothes would help them
get married. Also but one wonders also if there's a, if there's
like, if it's his recent daughter-in-law. If she's been living in the
house for the last ten years, you know, it might be a
little different. So, so
I don't know. Anyway, okay. So now it says like this, ואי
בנתיה לא נסיבן לא שבק בנתיה
ומשדר לכלתיה. v'ei b'noseih lo nesivan lo shavik b'noseih u'mshadar l'kallateih. So,
so it wasn't, it's the next line of the גמרא. Gemara Okay.
ואי בנתיה לא נסיבן, v'ei b'noseih lo nesivan, and if the daughter,
however if his daughters aren't yet married, לא שבק בנתיה ומשדר לכלתיה,
lo shavik b'noseih u'mshadar l'kallateih, he doesn't abandon his daughters, because again
the presumption is that he'd have to give them nice clothes in
order to help them look attractive and get married, so he would
not abandon them and give this to his daughter-in-law. Again I assume
though the daughter-in-law is limited to like a recent daughter-in-law. Okay. ומשדר
לכלתיה. u'mshadar l'kallateih. ההוא דאמר להו. Hahu d'amar lehu. So now somebody
said to them, whoever them is, to people who are around him,
נכסי לבנאי. nechasai l'vanai. "Let my property be to my בנים." banim
Now we know in Hebrew בנים banim normally means sons, but could
mean children. Okay. Now we normally interpret it to mean sons. The
only thing is he only has one son, but he has one
daughter. So are we going to interpret the word בנים banim. in
this context to mean my children?
You know, whatever children I'm going to have.
Okay, so let's see. Right. הוה ליה ברא וברתא. Havah lei b'ra
u'varta. He had a son and a daughter. מי קרי איניש לברא
בני? Mi kari inish l'v'ra banai? Would he call his, in one
son, would he call him "my sons"? Okay. So now the question
is why would he, if so, why would he have to do
it at all? Like why would he want to gift it to
his son if he only has one son, his son is going
to inherit it all anyway? Okay, so in our parenthesis we have,
this is a question of, well this is in the גרסא girsa
of the גמרא, Gemara תוספות Tosafot doesn't have this. לסלוקי ברתא מעישור
נכסי. l'saluki barta me'ishur nechasai. What we would be doing would be,
it would be effectively disinheriting his daughter because there's something called עישור
נכסים. ishur nechasim. That even though like we've seen, like even though
daughters don't inherit, wives don't inherit, people would try to do things
to get them back into the inheritance. So like we just discussed,
half to my wife and half to my sons, or whatever, my
wife and my sons. So by daughters there would be a standard
תנאי כתובה, tnai kesubah, which is a daughters would get a tenth
of the estate. Okay. So maybe by gifting it all rather than,
you know, he would, he would prevent them from getting those rights
of the תנאי כתובה. tnai kesubah. Gets back to a question which
was asked a few days ago, which is if he gifts all
his property to his sons rather than letting them inherit naturally, does
that also allow, it's like prevents the daughters from having the right
of being supported by the estate? Right, because then it's not working
through normal inheritance, it's just a gift. Okay, so that's at least
our גרסא. girsa.
תוספות Tosafot has a different explanation. Like by gifting the daughter they
don't get anything
and they don't get the, no gifting it to the son. If
it was, if he meant the son, why is he bothered gifting
it to the son? If he meant my single son, why did
he have to do it? His son would just inherit. So the
answer is no, he would do it as a gift rather than
as an inheritance so in order to get his daught... to prevent
his daughters from getting, you know, the תנאי כתובה. Tnai Kesuvah. Alright,
so that's what... so תוספות Tosfos has another answer. He says
where's תוספות?
Tosfos?
So he can get out of תנאי כתובה Tnai Kesuvah because
תנאי כתובה Tnai Kesuvah is only on what's left, so if he
gifted
there's nothing left, then they don't get. That's how he gets out.
Yeah,
except again we discussed earlier that in some cases the גמרא was
saying that if you're doing it as a type of מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnas shachiv mera, since it's modeled after ירושה, yerushah, it might
not get you out of those obligations. So it's still a little
unclear what the full parameters of that. מחלוקת Machlokes רמב"ם, Rambam, ראב"ד
Ra'avad about some of that stuff. Anyway, fine. So do we say
מי קרי אינשי לברא בני, mi kare inshi livra banai, do they
call a single son my sons, and it's all going to that
one son for whatever reasons, benefits that would have of gifting it,
okay? או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say לא קרי אינשי
לברא בני? lo kare inshi livra banai? He's not called... he wouldn't
call a single son sons. ולמוצויי לברתא במתנה אתא, u-l'motzu-ei l'barta b'matana
ata, and he's coming to include his daughter in the inheritance, okay?
And that's the whole point of this. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: תא
שמע, Ta shema, coming here: ובני דן חשים. U-vnei Dan Chushim. The
sons of Dan were חשים. Chushim. And so that was... right, I
mean it's a plural word חשים, Chushim, but it's presumably a person's
name, it's a proper name. So you see you can use the
word sons when only talking about one. אמר ליה רבא: Amlei Rava:
So רבא Rava says, דילמא כדתניא דבי חזקיה. dilma k'detanya d'vei Chizkiya.
No, maybe it's like דבי חזקיה d'vei Chizkiya taught a different meaning
of that פסוק. pasuk. שהיו מרובים כחושים של קני. She-hayu merubim k'chushim
shel kanei. They were as plentiful as like the reeds or whatever,
the brushes of reeds. So therefore חשים, Chushim, ובני דן חשים U-vnei
Dan Chushim is not a proper name, it means and the children
of Dan were like the reeds. Okay?
But he's listing all the other ones by name.
Right. It's obviously a very funny read of the פסוק. pasuk. אלא
אמר רבא: Ela amar Rava: So rather רבא Rava says: ובני פלוא
אליאב. U-vnei Pallu Eliav. Okay, that's a better one. So רב יוסף
אמר: Rav Yosef amar: ובני איתן עזריה. U-vnei Esan Azarya. Okay, and
that seems to end the discussion. Sometimes the פסוקים pesukim say בני
bnei when it's a single child, okay? And my sons would apply
even to a single son, okay? And therefore and so it's clearly
sad, because if you think the word בנים banim in Hebrew, Hebrew
is a gendered language, right? And and you know, it doesn't have
a neuter. So if you wanted to say children, how would you
say children? ילדים. Yeladim. What? ילדים. Yeladim.
My ילדים. Yeladim.
How... why would ילדים Yeladim also not mean boys?
I think it's still בנים.
banim, I guess, yeah, I guess, yeah.
So it's funny like how they would say, yeah, right.
I don't know, I don't know if there's a single word that
could mean children as a, you know, mixed as both men and
boys and girls.
I think בנים is used that way.
Yeah? Like בניכם ולא בנותיכם. bneichem v'lo bnoseichem. So no, but I'm
just saying it's very sad, meaning it's not like you start with
the assumption that it means sons, and since you find some basis
of saying that you could sometimes say sons in the plural and
mean single, we're going to limit it to sons, rather than starting
with the assumption that he only has one son and there's no
Hebrew word he could have used to have meant my children. Right?
I mean that's sort of what I would... if there was another
word and he used this word and anyway there's a bias towards
the sons, I would get it. But the fact that there's no
Hebrew word, it's like, to me that's a sort of sad conclusion.
צאצאים? Tze'etza'im? What? צאצאים. Tze'etza'im.
Oh, צאצאים. Tze'etza'im. But nobody,
nobody would use that.
Okay. Okay, my תולדות? toldos?
Okay.
So now our stark conclusion is that even for
one son it would go to the one son. Yep.
And and it... he would not now have to give her the
tenth of...
if that line is correct. And again, there's some debate in the
פוסקים poskim about if you gifted it all away but you gifted
it all away to your children, to your sons, does that get
you out of the כתובה kesuvah obligation? Okay. ההוא דאמר להו: Hahu
d'amar lehu: So now last case. Somebody said to somebody נכסי לבני.
nechasai livnai. My...
let my property be to my sons. Once again, okay. And but
הוה ליה ברא ובר ברא. havah lei bra u-var bra.
So he had a son and the son had a son, he
had a grandson. Okay? So קרי אינשי... kare inshi... so now that
we've already discerned that sons can mean singular and it would not
mean a daughter even if there's only one son, would it mean
a grandson? Okay? So קרי אינשי לבר ברא ברא
או לא? kare inshi l'var bra bra o lo? Do they call
a grandson a son or not? So the גמרא says... בני בנים
הרי הם כבנים? bnei banim ha-rei heim k'vanim? I know. רב חביבא
אמר: Rav Chaviva amar: קרי אינשי לבר ברא ברא. kare inshi l'var
bra bra. They do. מר בר רב אשי אמר: Mar bar Rav
Ashi amar: לא קרי אינשי לבר ברא ברא. lo kare inshi l'var
bra bra. They don't. תניא כוותיה דמר בר רב אשי: Tanyia k'vassay
d'Mar bar Rav Ashi: המודר הנאה מבנים מותר בבני בנים. Ha-mudar hana'ah
m'banim, mutar bivnei banim. If he said I'm not going to get
any הנאה hana'ah from my children, from my sons or whatever, he's
permitted... You're allowed to get הנאה hana'ah from your grandchildren. So
now of course other times we do say, right, and the רשב"ם
says as a halakhic point מותר בבני בנים mutar bi-vnei banim אבל
לעניין פריה ורביה חשיבי
כבנים. aval le-inyan piryah ve-rivyah chashivei k'banim. In areas, in some areas
of הלכה where grandchildren might count as children. Look, by יבום, yibum,
if there's even a grandchild or great grandchild. By ירושה, right, a
grandchild takes the place. But then what do people mean they say
sons? Okay? So people when they say sons might mean son in
the singular, but they don't mean grandsons. So at least I think
the conclusion of the גמרא would have been even harder to accept
if he would have had a son and a daughter and he
said בנים, it would have gone to the son. But if he
had a son and a grandson, the grandson would have gotten. Okay?
Now neither the grandson gets nor the daughter gets. It only goes
to the single son. Okay, let's start the next משנה. הניח בנים
גדולים וקטנים. hiniach banim gedolim u-ketanim.
Now
here we are now no longer with the daughters. We're back to
issues about the estate. And we've brought this in in the past
too. Somebody died, leftover an estate, and he has a lot of
kids, older ones, younger ones. It's a question whether the younger ones
really have to be minors here or we're just sort of saying
that it's a scenario where the older there are some sons that
are more interested in doing something with the estate and others are
sort of like not involved. Okay? והשביחו גדולים את הנכסים. ve-hishpichu gedolim
et ha-nechasim. And so the older ones came and before the estate
was divided and before they you know and they just went and
they just started making capital improvements. They planted, they hoed, they harvested,
whatever they did. Okay? So השביחו לאמצע. hishpichu la-emtza.
Everybody divides it. Now the question is why is that? Like if
I go into Michael's field and I plant it, or even if
we're partners. If I plant it you know if I go ahead
and do improvements that haven't been agreed upon, right, Michael at least
it's not like I'm totally giving up on you know my investment,
you know my effort, my whatever. Right? I mean Michael has to
pay me for you know for my efforts and then maybe we
split the benefit of it but it's not סתם, stam, right, at
least I invested all of that I did the planting and the
harvesting. At least the other kids should pay me for those for
that expense.
I can still recoup my costs?
No, that's not the assumption. The assumption is is just you know
what you spent you spent and everything is equally divided. Okay? At
least that's the way תוספות Tosafot explains it. So תוספות Tosafot says
fine, in a case of partners you're not מוחל mochel on your
costs and your expenses. But in a case
of you know children and a shared estate, if you don't say
anything otherwise, we're going to interpret your acts as you're doing it
on the benefit of the estate. But in terms of
money, probably if there was you know you could hand in your
receipts and get reimbursed for your expenses. Okay? But any effort you
exerted or whatever, if you're just סתם stam working and the estate
isn't divided and you haven't said anything, it's for the benefit of
the whole estate and gets divided. Okay? ואם אמרו ראו מה שהניח
אבא הרי אנו עושים ואוכלים. ve-im amru re'u mah she-hiniach abba harei
anu osim ve-ochlim. But if they get up and they say look,
we've got this estate, we want to start making a profit, okay,
I want to let you know that I'm going to be working
on it, you know it's going to take us time for probate
court and to divide the whole thing or whatever, but I'm going
to be working on it and I expect to keep my effort
the profit that I make to myself. Okay? Or that's what the
group of older kids could say. הרי אנו עושים ואוכלים. harei anu
osim ve-ochlim. השביחו לעצמן. hishpichu le-atzman. Then they get to keep what
they earn for themselves. Okay? So they don't have to divide it.
Okay? Now so assuming again that the younger ones are not objecting,
not doing they have an opportunity to say wait, we want to
participate, we want to whatever, they're being silent so or whoever represents
them is being silent, so that allows for that arrangement.
וכן האשה שהשביחה את הנכסים השביחה לאמצע. ve-chen ha-isha she-hishpichah et ha-nechasim
hishpichah la-emtza. So for a woman who was an heir and the
גמרא is going to figure out how this is possible.
Okay? And she's an heir together with the sons, sort of like
what we saw before. Okay? And she goes ahead, she doesn't say
anything, so it's on benefit of the whole
estate. Okay? אם אמרה ראו מה שהניח לי בעלי הרי אני עושה
ואוכלת. im amrah re'u mah she-hiniach li ba'ali harei ani osah ve-ochelet.
If she makes a declaration that I'm going to do it and
I plan on keeping it for myself and if you want to
chip in and be a part of it you're able to, but
otherwise I'm keeping the benefit for myself, then השביחה לעצמה. hishpichah le-atzmah.
She gets to keep it. So you go to the two extremes.
You never have a middle case which is like you pay me
for my efforts and we split the profit. It's either assumed to
be doing it totally on behalf of the estate or if I
make a declaration, I'm totally doing it on my behalf and your
silence is your allowing me to keep it all for myself. All
right, we'll continue with this tomorrow.